<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-27T00:49:21+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gaurav Hoskote</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>Gaurav Hoskote</name><email>gaurav.hoskote@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Simple things you can do to get better at Machine Learning.</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/get-better-at-ml/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simple things you can do to get better at Machine Learning." /><published>2023-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/future-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/get-better-at-ml/"><![CDATA[<!-- This post will show up by default. To disable scheduling of future posts, edit `config.yml` and set `future: false`.  -->
<p>Machine learning is a complex and rapidly evolving field that can be daunting to navigate, even for seasoned professionals. As someone who has taken courses in machine learning and experimented with various techniques, I know firsthand how challenging it can be to improve your skills and gain a deeper understanding of the subject.</p>

<p>However, over time, I’ve discovered that there are some simple steps you can take to improve your understanding of machine learning and become a more effective practitioner. Through trial and error, I’ve identified a few key strategies that have helped me gain a better grasp of the concepts and techniques involved.</p>

<p>In this blog post, I want to share these strategies with you. Whether you’re just starting out in machine learning or you’re looking to improve your skills, these tips can help you gain a deeper understanding of the subject and become a more effective practitioner. So, without further ado, here are the simple things I did to get a bit better at machine learning.</p>

<h3 id="solve-ml-math-problems-by-hand">Solve ML Math problems by hand:</h3>
<p>Understanding the math behind machine learning algorithms is crucial to truly mastering them. By solving problems by hand, you’ll gain a deeper understanding of the underlying concepts and be better equipped to apply them in practice. This can also help you identify where you might be making mistakes in your code. Earlier, I believed that I had a firm grasp of the mathematical principles underlying many algorithms, but it wasn’t until I attempted to work through the math myself that I realized my understanding was inadequate/incomplete.</p>

<h3 id="try-to-explain-concepts-to-people">Try to explain concepts to people:</h3>
<p>Explaining concepts to others is a great way to solidify your own understanding of them. When you can explain a concept in simple terms, it means you truly understand it yourself. Additionally, teaching others can help you identify any gaps in your own knowledge.</p>

<h3 id="code-it-preferably-from-scratch">Code it (preferably from scratch):</h3>
<p>While using pre-built libraries and frameworks can be convenient, coding machine learning algorithms from scratch can help you gain a deeper understanding of how they work. Example: You can code a simple 2-layer neural network to understand how back-propagation works.</p>

<h3 id="understand-the-concept-in-2-dimensions-and-trust-it-to-work-on-higher-dimensions">Understand the concept in 2 dimensions and trust it to work on higher dimensions:</h3>
<p>Machine learning algorithms can become incredibly complex in higher dimensions, but understanding how they work in two dimensions is a good foundation for building that understanding. Trusting the concepts you’ve learned in two dimensions to work in higher dimensions can help you avoid getting overwhelmed and improve your overall understanding of the algorithm. For example, take a classification task that requires us to find out if a point lies above or below a line. Once we understand how the algorithm works to classify points in this simple 2D case, we can be confident that it will work for more complex classification tasks in higher dimensions, even though the boundary may be more difficult to visualize.</p>

<h3 id="findconnect-with-people-who-are-passionate-about-it">Find/Connect with people who are passionate about it:</h3>
<p>Surrounding yourself with others who are passionate about machine learning can help you stay motivated and inspired. Additionally, networking with others in the field can lead to new opportunities and help you stay up-to-date on the latest trends and techniques.</p>

<h3 id="try-to-read-research-papers-on-your-own">Try to read research papers on your own:</h3>
<p>Reading research papers can help you stay current with the latest developments in machine learning. Additionally, it can help you gain a deeper understanding of the underlying theory behind different algorithms and techniques. If the idea of reading new research papers seems overwhelming, one helpful strategy is to start by reading papers on concepts that you already understand well. This can be a great way to build up your confidence and develop the skills you need to understand more complex research papers over time. As you become more comfortable with the process of reading and interpreting research papers, you can begin to explore more cutting-edge research and stay up-to-date with the latest developments in the field.</p>

<h3 id="using-kaggle">Using Kaggle:</h3>
<p>Although I haven’t had much time to dedicate to Kaggle due to my Masters program, I’ve found it to be a highly valuable resource for practicing machine learning and applying it to real-world problems. Kaggle offers opportunities to learn from others’ techniques, compete with peers, and receive feedback on your work. I highly recommend exploring this platform to improve your skills.</p>

<p>By incorporating these habits into your machine learning practice, you can improve your understanding of the underlying concepts and become a more effective practitioner.</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Hoskote</name><email>gaurav.hoskote@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Machine learning is a complex and rapidly evolving field that can be daunting to navigate, even for seasoned professionals. As someone who has taken courses in machine learning and experimented with various techniques, I know firsthand how challenging it can be to improve your skills and gain a deeper understanding of the subject.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Top Machine Learning Courses that are too good to be Free!</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/top_ml_courses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top Machine Learning Courses that are too good to be Free!" /><published>2022-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/blog-post-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/posts/top_ml_courses/"><![CDATA[<p>For the past several months I have been trying to master the field of Machine Learning. I am no expert in this field and am still in the process of learning, but in this post I would like to share a few Free Resources available online that helped me a lot on this journey.</p>

<p>Mentioned below are a few of them…</p>

<h1 id="courses-for-machine-learning-and-deep-learning-theory">Courses for Machine Learning and Deep Learning Theory:</h1>
<h3 id="cs229--machine-learning-by-stanford-university">CS229 — Machine Learning by Stanford University.</h3>

<ul>
  <li>The latest version of this course uploaded on YouTube is taught by Prof. Anand Avati formerly taught by Andrew Ng.</li>
  <li>This Course is an advanced version of the famous Machine Learning Course by Andrew Ng on Coursera.</li>
  <li>The course covers everything starting from Linear Algebra all the way up to Reinforcement Learning.</li>
  <li>Course links: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jGwO_UgTS7I&amp;list=PLoROMvodv4rMiGQp3WXShtMGgzqpfVfbU">CS229 Autumn 2018</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KzH1ovd4Ots&amp;list=PLoROMvodv4rNH7qL6-efu_q2_bPuy0adh">CS229 Summer 2019</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cs231n--convolutional-neural-networks-for-visual-recognition">CS231N — Convolutional Neural Networks for Visual Recognition.</h3>

<ul>
  <li>This might arguably be the best course I have ever taken. There are 2 versions of this course available on YouTube — Winter 2016 and Spring 2017.</li>
  <li>The Winter 2016 course is taught by Andrej Karapathy and the course is uploaded on his YouTube Channel. The explanation of each and every concept is detailed yet lucid.</li>
  <li>The Spring 2017 version taught by Justin Johnson has a few extra topics covered compared to the 2016 version. The CS231N team has taken efforts to keep the syllabus up to date.</li>
  <li>Course Links: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NfnWJUyUJYU&amp;list=PLkt2uSq6rBVctENoVBg1TpCC7OQi31AlC">CS231N Winter 2016</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vT1JzLTH4G4&amp;list=PL3FW7Lu3i5JvHM8ljYj-zLfQRF3EO8sYv">CS231N Spring 2017</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="cs224n--nlp-with-deep-learning">CS224N — NLP with Deep Learning.</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Taught by Christopher Manning, this course is about Deep Learning techniques used in Natural Language Processing Tasks.</li>
  <li>I personally feel they could have included more code examples as it could be a little tricky for people with no math background to bridge the gap from theory to code.</li>
  <li>You can also check out CS224U — Natural Language Understanding which covers topics in similar areas.</li>
  <li>Course Links: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8rXD5-xhemo&amp;list=PLoROMvodv4rOhcuXMZkNm7j3fVwBBY42z">CS224N</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tZ_Jrc_nRJY&amp;list=PLoROMvodv4rObpMCir6rNNUlFAn56Js20">CS224U</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="courses-for-building-a-math-background">Courses for building a math background:</h1>
<h3 id="statistics-110-probability-by-harvard-university">Statistics 110: Probability by Harvard University.</h3>
<ul>
  <li>People referring to this course solely for learning ML concepts can skip the counting part and start from lecture 8 (Random variables).</li>
  <li>I still recommend watching the entire course as there as references to topics covered in previous lectures like Vandermonde’s identity etc and also because its a lot of fun!</li>
  <li>Much of what is covered in this series will help you understand CS229 (by Anand Avati) as it requires firm background in probability and Statistics.</li>
  <li>Course Link: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KbB0FjPg0mw&amp;list=PL2SOU6wwxB0uwwH80KTQ6ht66KWxbzTIo">Statistics 110</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="linear-algebra-and-multivariate-calculus">Linear Algebra and Multivariate Calculus:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>I have not taken an entire course because I was fairly confident in this area but there are videos uploaded on YouTube by MIT Opencourseware on both these topics.</li>
  <li>Course Links: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PxCxlsl_YwY&amp;list=PL4C4C8A7D06566F38">Multivariate Calculus</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZK3O402wf1c&amp;list=PL49CF3715CB9EF31D&amp;index=1">Linear Algebra</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Bonus: People uncomfortable with Math and Probability can refer to DeepLearning.ai. (YouTube Channel) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/Deeplearningai">link</a></p>

<h1 id="programming-channels-for-mldl">Programming Channels for ML/DL:</h1>
<ul>
  <li>I used Pytorch documentation which has enough code samples. But if you are accustomed to consuming content in the form of videos then Sentdex, Krish Naik, Deep Lizard, Codebasics, are some YouTube channels that you might want to check.</li>
  <li>Aladdin Persson is a very underrated YouTuber whose Github repository and YouTube Channel has helped me learn CNN architectures. Link: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/AladdinPersson">Aladdin’s YouTube</a> and <a href="https://github.com/aladdinpersson">Github</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>These were a few resources that I knew of. Feel free to share any resources that helped you too. :)</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Hoskote</name><email>gaurav.hoskote@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the past several months I have been trying to master the field of Machine Learning. I am no expert in this field and am still in the process of learning, but in this post I would like to share a few Free Resources available online that helped me a lot on this journey.]]></summary></entry></feed>